software engineering radio episode 101
debugging with andreas hello this is
software engineering radio the podcast
for professional developers on the web
at s e - radio dotnet SE radio prints
irrelevant and detailed discussions and
interviews on soft engineering topics
every 10 days thanks to our audience and
the partners listed on our website for
supporting the Contra
[Music]
hello everybody welcome to this new
episode of software engineering radio in
the new century episode 101 this one is
about debugging and specifically Delta
debugging with Andreas Salam from
Saarland University but before we get
started we have to make a somewhat sad
announcement it's about the SE Radio get
together we've only received six or
seven position papers amounting to like
10 or 12 or maybe 15 people and that's
far too low to organize to get together
the deadline for the papers was May 1st
sorry June 1st and I've mixed mess
something up so I said in the podcast
June 15th so we waited until June 15th
but still we didn't get any additional
papers so we had to cancel so I guess I
see radio will stay a virtual endeavor
without meeting in person so sad but
true well let's get on with the episode
yeah well as I said this one is about
debugging Delta debugging with Andreas
hello
have fun so welcome employers to the
show welcome so why don't you introduce
yourself to your to our listeners or
yeah I'm a professor at Holland
University which has a very good
computer science department and I've
been there for six years now and before
that I well I did my PhD I did a typical
academic career with a strong practical
side and especially debugging okay and
the the reason I found out about you was
actually that's not true
I read this beautiful codebook and there
is a chapter of yours on beautiful
debugging but I also heard about Delta
debugging before so so that's one angle
to it so before we discuss your specific
thing which is this Delta debugging
stuff let's discuss debugging in general
a little bit so what is debugging
debugging is
the action of finding the defect that
causes a specific failure that is your
program crashes and you want to figure
out why it failed and you want to fix
the program such that the failure no
longer occurs and and okay yeah that's
very general definition of course and by
the way we've recently had this episode
with Bob Denver who talked about
fault-tolerant systems and he explained
the terms like fault failure error and
one how one leads to the other so we're
now trying to find the root cause not
the final problem yes and it's a long
series of errors so first sometimes the
programmer makes an error this results
in an error in the code this then when
being executed may result in an error in
the program State and this then results
in an error in the program result and
all these errors have distinct names
their error of the programmer is called
a mistake the error in the code is
called a fault or defect in the state is
called an infection and when it gets and
when you see it the error in the program
execution that's when it's called a
failure right so the final thing at the
end of the chain is the face okay so um
let's let's look a little bit about how
debugging works in principle I mean that
there is always the problem that you
have some kind of tool that you used to
inspect and the program needs to tell
the tool where it is or these kind of
things well according to some of the
debugging is totally trivial our
somerville has written a nice book on
software engineering it's for beginners
and he explains the debugging process in
four steps first you locate the error
then you design a repair for the error
then you test the repair this is
essentially what you have to do of
course the first thing is how to locate
the error which is by far the most
complicated thing of all right right
exactly so so well so that's something
where we're tools are obviously used as
we all know this is right yes but the
tools were using are the tools were
using the typical interactive debuggers
I'm afraid to say are not really
adequate for the kind of tasks debuggers
have to do in particular because
ordinary interactive debuggers in terms
of their language the way you interact
with the program are you set breakpoints
you execute stuff this is a very very
low level and there's virtually no way
you can reason
words which is the typical way of
reasoning when you're debugging so the
program has to be executed forward but
you have to reason backwards in order to
understand it very good point you didn't
think of that before
one last thing before we like go to the
like the core of the discussion I work
quite a bit in model demand development
so the question is always how do you
debug models and one thing that comes up
as well and generated code you have to
put in some callbacks so in order for
debugging to work you I guess always
need some what's called debug
information and in the in the in the
binary or whatever kind of thing you
want to debug and we need want to do
interactive debugging you indeed need to
have a relationship between your
original source code and the state yours
you're seeing on the screen when you're
doing model driven development one needs
to carry that relationship further up to
the model right and I'm not sure how
much our how much this is supported by
current model driven development tools
sure I mean that varies and any work
case you have to build it yourself but
but the point there is you have to
somehow instrument the programs to make
it debuggable if you want to do
interactive debugging if you want to do
interactive debugging you have to
actually have to find a way to interrupt
the program execution and observe the
state and to observe the state at some
higher level of abstraction that is not
as a series of bits and bytes spread
across the memory but of course to see
the objects in the very same way that
you originally defined them in your
model or in your source code right so we
kind of distinguish between debugging
and interactive debugging what are the
debugging techniques are there I would
guess that 90% of our listeners only
know you know this nice little tool you
can step through stuff which is then
called interactive debugging that's
right our and this used to be the state
of the art until say 10 years ago
however there's a very nice set of tools
and techniques available right now that
automate most of the debugging that
automatically point you to locations
where the error is most likely to be
that automatically identify causes of
the failure in terms of a program input
in terms of program state or in terms of
changes to the program code you see
debugging is essentially a search
process makes it different from all
other software engineering activities
where you essentially construct
something when
construct something you can plan how
long it will take more or less however
when you're debugging since this is a
search process it can take you anytime
between five minutes five hours or five
days maybe even five weeks to find a
single bug and this lack of this lack of
being able to plan how long it will take
is the major risk about debugging
because you never know when it's going
to end and this is why this is also why
programmers spend nights after nights
chasing bugs and not coming home with
their families and they sent their
social lies which is why debugging is
definitely an area which is in great
need to be automated as much as possible
okay so but instead of automating one
thing would also be to make it a little
bit more systematic so you have this
thing the scientific method and
systematic debugging what is the
scientific method and how does that
relate to debugging or does it maybe not
well most programmers I know and I think
I'm not I'm not that much of an
exception immediately jump to the
interactive debugger as soon as you see
a failure and then you poke around you
step forward step backward poke in
different directions you can do this for
maybe five minutes or so if you haven't
found anything then it's time to step
back from the computers also time to
step back from the interactive debugger
and actually think this means that you
have to be explicit to what to start
with how does the failure manifests
itself why is this wrong and simply
stating this simply writing this up on a
piece of paper or telling to a friend
already solves two thirds of all
debugging problems sure that's that the
doc debugging so explain the problem to
your dog cuz it's next to you and
suddenly you know what the problem is in
fact the bug exactly that's that the
first thing you need to be explicit when
you're debugging is the next thing is
once you're explicit about the problem
you can think about possible problem
causes and these problem causes of
course also have to be written down in
some explicit way the scientific method
tells you the cause for a specific
observation in nature typically but this
is not so much different from debugging
because as soon as you're debugging your
program becomes part of some
inexplicable phenomenon that's very much
the same as the nature too so you can
observe you can apply the same
techniques so you come up with a
and then you come and then you need to
design a way to test your hypothesis and
you make an experiment and depending on
the outcome of the experiment you refine
your hypothesis or or you reject your
hypothesis and this process can be
followed pretty systematically again by
being explicit writing down what you
think the hypothesis is writing down the
experiment writing down the result this
seems somewhat Edu's at first but if you
think about that by writing that down
you can interrupt your debugging process
anytime come back next morning with
fresh mind you only really save time on
that and this is simply a systematic
process trying out stuff systematically
rather than poke around and examining
what other greats of the program is
doing but which has nothing to do with
the error you're looking at yeah exactly
so that's kind of smart approach to
debugging and one could say that
considering debugging as a search
problem is more like a brute-force
attack so what is what what does it mean
to consider debugging a search problem
essentially this means that you have
various search domains in which you're
searching for causes for instance this
is a nice story to tell when the first
versions of Mozilla of the Mozilla
browser were released this was in 2001
our the Mozilla team had lots and lots
of trouble with bug reports that plenty
of bug reports but there were but they
had no way to find out what was the
relevant part of each bug report so
essentially the bug report said I'm
loading this web page and I'm printing
it out and it doesn't work but the web
page in question would have would have
thousands and thousands of lines and you
wondered well not everything on this web
page will be relevant for making the
program fail yep so what they did
actually if he called for volunteers on
the net for volunteers that would help
them simplify these bug reports and they
actually gave out prizes such as a
stuffed gecko animals the the little
green dragon that will be the mascot of
the Mozilla team and teams and a t-shirt
signed by the entire team and all and
within hours they had dozens and dozens
of volunteers and of simplified bug
reports which is very nice but on the
other hand simplifying such a bug report
is a very very straightforward thing you
don't need to be a programmer to do that
what you do is you
the input take half of the input see
whether it works whether the failure is
still reproduced yes if it works you do
another half of the input this is the
scientific method at its easiest it
simply reduce the search space and go
along until you eventually narrow that
down to a very very tiny input okay so
so this is basically what brought you to
the Delta debugging idea right exactly
so so I was totally amazed at that how
you could have all these volunteers do
that manually which was which is so
stupid well he could have been done
could have been done by monkeys for
instance yeah and well they actually
called for volunteers who didn't have
any clue about well you didn't actually
it actually advertised the whole thing
you don't have to have any programming
knowledge
Isaac HTML knowledge knowledge suffices
I said well if this is so easy I can I
can just as well automate sure yes and
the idea is that as soon as you have an
automated test that checks whether a
specific failure is still there or not
all you need all you need in this case
is a strategy that does this
minimization for your cutting away half
of the input see whether it still works
at cutting away other parts the
systematic cutting down of inputs and
repeating and repeating again the
automated test until you come up with a
with a very very simple input that
produces the test and this was the
beginning of Delta debugging that's also
where the name Delta comes from where
you change the input by increments or
deltas exactly it has it has two if
there's two explanations to the name one
is the Delta that you applied to the
input the other one this is a variant of
Delta debugging which tries to find a
minimal difference between two inputs
and this again this difference is a
delta there's one important thing you
mentioned kind of on the side which is
kind of essential you need an automated
test you need something that determines
automatically whether well whether the
failure in that sense still manifests
itself or not so that's actually an
interesting relationship to test driven
and all this tests hyper should go to
the to the justified idea of making test
an essential part of software
development
this is totally right so in test-driven
development you do have two distinct
benefits from writing your tests first
thing is your test serves as a
specification the second thing is your
I can later on be run in order to
protect you from change impact you don't
want to now you get a third benefit that
is as soon as you have an automated test
you also have automated debugging in the
sense that you can automatically be
brought to a cause of the failure it's
that now come diverging a bit but it's
that also a technique that some of the
automatic test generation test coverage
tools like agitator or what a cheat are
I don't know which one you know what I
mean
do they use this kind of stuff too is
that related it these techniques can be
very easily combined with automatic test
generation and I'll be visiting a GTR in
March you don't have to talk about that
ok let's look at this Delta debugging a
little bit closer we are the example you
gave initially the manual Delta
debugging by the Mozilla folks was
basically changing the input to the
program the program being more or less
the HTML renderer and the program the
HTML page so in that case you actually
debug a problem in program input yes
what else can you do back because
typically if I considered debugging I'm
not trying to debug the program input
this very much depends on how much your
input points you to specific places in
your program in case of Mozilla for
instance we eventually found out that
printing a select tag for instance in
HTML caused the browser to crash and of
course there's one specific place in the
program where these select tags are
handled so this very this can be very
very useful also think about random
tests for instance you're you're testing
a sequel server for instance and so
you're generating large SQL queries that
cause your sequel server to produce
wrong results I should come to a sequel
vendor and tell them hey here's my 30
line nested sequel whatsoever come on
and it crashes and the vendor will tell
you well that's not on our priority list
because nobody ever didn't nobody ever
does such queries but if you minimize
that say to two line thing and these two
lines still produced a failure the
vendor will become very very upset
because not only do you have a means to
point people to the error but you can
also easily generalize you can
characterize the error you can edit
identify duplicates and all this happens
when you do when you're dealing with
input right so this is actually exactly
the point where you try to narrow down a
test case so everybody knows yes
precisely what the problem is
exactly
once we once we did this for input
however we were also thinking about
other applications and one interesting
application is doing this for changes so
changes of what changes to your program
code ah so think about the version
history or think about a very simple
example your computer still worked
yesterday and now you're applying some
patches some changes to your system and
suddenly it doesn't work anymore and you
wonder well why did that happen and as
soon as you have an old version of your
program that worked in which it test
worked and now you have a new version in
which to test no longer works yeah you
can again apply Delta debugging in order
to figure out what the subset of these
changes it was that actually caused the
failure so in this case you debug the
program structure which is more or less
that's a the classical case of debugging
that most people know best I guess
exactly in that case in that case we're
actually dealing with a program code and
we're making changes to the program code
it's actually pretty funny to say that
if you apply just a subset of changes
you get pretty weird programs out of
this okay so that's it's also advisable
to run this in a sandbox and this is and
this is definitely something that would
be extremely tedious to do manually
so this is where automation fully fully
plays the game and we realized that for
a German company called a web de who are
who are a deep in the integration of
different open source programs and okay
so we did this for them and initially
initially our plan was to make this an
eclipse plugin and what we called
one-click debugging so your your unit
test fails and our plugin would
automatically record all the results of
the unit tests and if it would find that
some earlier configuration existed in
which this very unit test worked then it
would automatically narrow down the
change and after a couple of after a
couple of minutes these processes are
not really fast
after a couple of minutes it would
automatically identify the change that
led to that let it to the failure are
actually the people at web de called
the blame ohmmeter because because it
would immediately point people to the to
the to the change that made the program
fail but unfortunately our idea of
one-click debugging didn't turn out well
so because it turned out that we didn't
even need that one click so we made this
0 click debugging as soon as a genuine
it test would fail in the background our
plugin would automatically set itself
into motion and and isolate the failure
inducing change so it means that what
you did is whenever you checked in
something you also checked in that the
triggering results so you could compare
that to different what was the
granularity of the you know of the
changes you did was it the local history
or was it like the change in CBS or
wherever
well when I first implemented this this
was all a set of scripts and it will
only work on CBS history but when my
stood out in Booga did that for web 2a
he actually also took the local history
into account so we were able to really
narrow that down this also works in you
know when you're doing manual works so
suppose you work in the morning so this
works you down a couple of changes no
longer works and all of us and and after
a couple of minutes or in that case
seconds our little dialog pops up and
tells you this is the place and this is
the change my student actually also
inserted a dialog that allowed you to
revert this change that such that the
failure in question no longer occurred
we are still discussing whether this is
a good idea because well reverting the
change it will make the failure go away
but this is not necessarily this will
not necessarily result in a complete
correction of the program because it
don't have a hundred percent coverage no
because simply applying this change may
make this failure go away but may cause
other failures later on in yeah but that
means that other tests would fail if you
had 100 percent coverage coverage yes
but but my idea was always well the
programmer is the last one to take
responsibility the program absolutely
applies so I have a couple of following
questions to that but let's first look
at the third aspect which is to do back
program State that's for me the most
abstract to understand so what's that
this was a pretty pretty weird story
the
thing is that if you look at input you
can isolate input that cause the program
to fail so far so good but input doesn't
necessarily you to the right location in
the code because input is processed all
along the execution of the program think
about a compiler for instance you have
some input say a plus sign or whatsoever
and this gets processed all along the
entire chain of optimizations that
happened within the compiler code
generation and all so it would be very
very difficult to even if you know that
some part of the input causes the
failure to locate a specific place
within the compiler so you actually have
to go and decompose the execution of the
program into individual steps where each
steps takes input from the previous
component think of a pipeline and then
you can see a program execution as a
series of program states so the very
first component takes the input produces
a state the next component takes a state
produces another state and so on until
the final state is being well displayed
to the user or written to a file server
so you see the program execution as a
series of state and once you do that you
can also narrow down narrow down
differences in state that caused the
program to fail okay and how do you
actually track that state I mean that
sounds to me like a pretty abstract
concept it is both a very abstract
concept but it's also full of
technicalities so we implemented a tool
that would extract the state from actual
executions and we would do so by
instrumenting an ordinary debugger we
write other variables take the values
and if it's a pointer we expand the
appropriate data structure so that we
arrive at a fixed point so we'd actually
extract all the accessible variables
including everything on the heap and the
stack and so on with all their values
and once you have such a state you can
also manipulate it well as you can do in
ordinary debug sources as well and if
you have two states for instance a state
from a passing run where the test passes
and a state from a failing run where the
test fails you can go for a diff between
these two so this is somewhat
complicated because the state is
essentially a graph yes and so you have
to look forward if within graphs but
this is also something that can be
solved and now you have differences
between these state
and if you have a state from a passing
run and a state from a failing run you
know that the difference between these
two states is the difference that caused
the program to fail and so the next idea
is once you have these differences you
need to narrow down these differences
again in order to point to the state
that makes the program fail you talked
about this web da stuff on the other
hand side in your chapter for the book
you talked about Delta debugging being a
prototype problem because it kind of
doesn't scale the big problems or
because it's too slow because it's
essentially brute force so how how
realistic is that how much practical use
is there where's the tool I can download
a sense for question I guess in terms of
input are there's two there's a tool
called Delta from Berkley which you can
download but the algorithm is so simple
it's it fits on a single it fits on
twenty lines of Python code
yeah so for input you can easily
implement this yourself and by the same
way adapted to a code is being used in
many many places including at Microsoft
at s ap whenever you're doing something
it's so easy to implement it straight
forward so the notion that it's a
prototype problem isn't oh god that did
I get this wrong or or what I mean it I
think it does say it in the paper it
depends on it depends on what you're
applying this to you're applying this to
input it's so straightforward you can
assess it you can just just implement it
as it you implement it on changes there
you actually have a plug-in to download
called DD change you can download this
for eclipse and make it work immediately
if you apply this to a program state
however this is very fresh experimental
this is not something I would recommend
for general use okay and and the search
algorithm you're using here is is it
like I mean I was thinking about using I
don't know genetic algorithms that you
actually don't you know do the changes
systematically and therefore increase
the speed of the search is that
something you're playing with or is it
really just basically narrowing down
half you know like first taking this
half and that half and then taking the
half the works and so on well when I
designed this whole thing actually
looked very hard into appropriate
genetic algorithms and searched other
games but wouldn't find anything that
fit so we don't really but what the
Delta debugging argument actually is you
can see it as a binary search this is
the base of the whole thing first half
second half yeah
but it comes with a twist if the if
neither the first half nor the second
half lead to result for instance you
want to minimize think neither the first
half of the input works not the second
half of the input works then comes
specific twist rather than splitting the
input in two parts it splits it in four
parts eight parts or the other way
around it takes away it doesn't take
away the first half but takes away the
first quarter second quarter third
quarter and so on and then it takes away
the first eight then the second eight
and by taking away smaller and smaller
pieces of the input it's able to come
down very good it's able to narrow down
the input pretty quickly still yeah but
without going through the hassle of
taking away say single characters from
very beginning which would be a very
very tip okay I mentioned already before
or well we talked about this
relationship to testing because you
can't do Delta debugging if you don't
have a test that automatically verifies
the the point they are up and and I had
this question here in my script that
talks about what's the relationship to
to testing because some people say you
don't need to debug if you have enough
unit tests or if you do test drone
development the need for debugging goes
down so I mean that's not necessarily I
mean the kind of debugging you propose
isn't debugging in there in the in the
sense everybody does so it's more like a
a systematic exercise of the tests you
have so the point is what's the real is
there anything more to say on the
relationship between tester and
development and Delta debugging
definitely because because what
techniques like Delta debugging do they
give you causes but the do not
necessarily necessarily give you errors
in order to define that something is an
error you need a specification yeah that
is you need for instance unit tests
assertions in your code yeah our
contract driven develop an essay like in
the Eifel programming language is a very
good example for that and essentially
the more checks you have in your code
the check whether something is an error
or not the easier it is to detect errors
and also the easier it is to do to
locate the error if you have a
in which the pre and post conditions are
clearly defined and checked the
preconditions are all satisfied the post
condition is violated then you
definitely know what the error is in
that very function and therefore this is
of course another way to automate
automate debugging the more tests you
have and the more assertions you have in
your code the easier your debugging life
will be mm-hmm yeah absolutely
okay so to wrap this up let's let's
discuss a little bit other approaches to
automatic program well I shouldn't say
maybe other approaches to automatic
program verification but your approach
is certainly a way to help you automate
some aspect of verifying that a program
works and then if it doesn't work why so
is there any relationship to static
analysis tools and some of these things
yes of course because aesthetic analysis
tool will definitely rule out a number
of possibilities in static analysis tool
will tell you for instance during
debugging that there are places which
simply cannot have any influence yeah so
static analysis can can come in very
handy in places and the second thing is
of course that static an aesthetic
analysis tools are great tools for
detecting potential errors such as
here's the potential overflow or here's
a potential or here's a potential loop
that never ends yeah and like stuff okay
so but there isn't any specific
collaboration because when you talk
about programs state when we did the
episode on on static analysis that's
also term it came up because of course
staring analysis tool has to try to
understand the program and abstract the
program stay to meaningful you know not
just a bunch of variables but to a
meaningful state that well so that that
sounded like there is a relationship
there or there's there's a group of
Neelam Gupta in Arizona for instance who
has combined Delta debugging techniques
with static and dynamic analysis
techniques and they've been very
successful in particular combining
multiple approaches such as program
analysis and these experimental
approaches search processes in Delta
debugging is one of the most promising
ways to even to improve the accuracy and
the speed of these techniques even
further so we talked about Delta
debugging as a way of automating some of
the tedious tasks of manually finding an
arab is there other approaches you I
don't know
maybe you're working on today or that
you've worked on in the past or you know
about that that that kind of automate
that and help people get rid of some of
the tedious aspects of debugging the
general idea of the work we're doing
right now is to exploit all the
information there is from program realms
and from program development and we've
seen Delta debugging we look at the
changes we looked at the automated test
there we look at the code we look at
program state and there's so much more
to exploit and which is recorded in
daily process such as friends and bug
reports the change history profiles of
how the software is being used emails
between developers models y'all already
ordered to mention that yeah and all
this is being recorded in appropriate
databases and what we're doing is we
mined these databases for instance to
figure out where the where in your
program the most bugs occurred in the
past this is obviously information you
can use for debugging because you can
focus on the usual suspects yeah and but
this is also information that can be
very relevant for managers for instance
when you're designing when you're
deciding where to test most because you
focus on those place where the most bugs
are and you can use that to identify
patterns that in your program structures
in your program that typically correlate
with a higher risk of making mistakes
and once you once you bring that to some
sort of climax you end up in tools that
assist you while you're programming and
they tell you this is something that
looks like that this looks like
something that should be tested more
because from history we know that there
that this structure results in many bugs
or this is something that this is the
way of interacting with a module that
others haven't done before so maybe
you'd look at some other code example
and of course during debugging these are
places I would look at first because
these are the most likely places to
contain the bug so our long-term vision
in say 10 or 20 years now is to have
some sort of your programming
environment acting as a body while
you're programming as an assistant while
your program has think of it like a
navigation system that tells you that
tells you where you are where you should
go that tells you when you leave the
track and it also tells you how long it
will take
to get there cool so I think we're
nearing the end of the of the show so is
there anything else I should have asked
anything else you want to say I think my
idea is that no programmer should go
should get home late because he or she
has been debugging so so my idea is at
the end of the day press a button
look at your notes go home come back the
next morning even the fresh mind your
computer is there to do the Teddy stuff
so it's not you so let your computer
doing all the hard work so in some sense
it's it's a continuation of the trends
we've seen before with automatic builds
we have automated test execution we have
in at least some environments automatic
code generation from more semantic
higher-level models so automatic
debugging sounds like another building
block in that next step of automating
software development yes eventually our
keyboards will have just one single
button to do it I mean but the only
thing is that I suspect that there's
going to be a second button which is do
what I really mean and do what I should
have men do sure what I should have met
we're not there yet so at least let's
take some of these tedious tasks away
from the programmer and move them over
to the machine okay thank you and today
is very much for being on the show thank
you
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website and
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for su radio for example by clicking on
the Digg reddit delicious and slash dog
buttons to contact the team lease an
email to team and SC radio net or if
it's specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license
please see the website for details
thanks to Charlie Crowell and the pot
safe music network for the music used in
this show the song is called Vegas hard
rock shuffle